Hunter, B. mss., 1962-1979 LMC 1535
Lilly Library
Hunter, B. mss.
1962-1979
Lilly Library
Jones, Jim, 1931-1978
Hunter, Barton, 1908-1988
LMC 1535
1 Box 1 standard
The Hunter, B. mss., circa 1962-1979, consists of correspondence, notes, clippings, et cetera of Jim Jones, 1931-1978, and of Barton Hunter, 1908-1988, relating to People's Temple Christian Church of Indianapolis, Indiana and to Jones's Christian missions in South America.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Jim Jones, 1938-1978, was born James Warren Jones, May 13, 1931 in Crete, Indiana. Jones went to high school in Richmond, Indiana, graduating in January 1949. He entered Indiana University immediately following graduation, married Marceline Baldwin in June 1949 and then moved to Indianapolis in 1950 where he sporadically attended Butler University, receiving a B.Ed in 1961. Jones opened Indianapolis's first biracial church in 1954 and renamed it Peoples Temple the following year. In 1960 the Temple joined the Disciples of Christ. In 1961 he became director of the Indianapolis Human Relations Commission then spent the next two years on a mission in Brazil. In 1965 he moved with about fifty of his followers to Redwood City, California, and opened branches of the Temple in San Francisco and Los Angeles. In 1974 the Temple leased more than 3,000 acres of Guyana jungle and members began clearing the land for agriculture and the building of Jonestown. Four years later Jones demanded that his followers commit mass suicide by drinking grape-flavored poison and then apparently shot himself, November 18, 1978.
Barton Hunter, 1908-1988, minister, was born in Birmingham, Alabama. He received his bachelors from Indiana University and his masters of divinity from the University of Chicago. Hunter was executive secretary of the Church in Society, one of the sections of the Disciples of Christ Christian Church, from 1952 to 1973. He first met Jim Jones in 1955 in Indianapolis through their work in the church. Hunter went on to serve as executive director of the pacifist organization Fellowship of Reconciliation and was one of the founders and first presidents of the Indiana Civil Liberties Union.
Scope and Content Note
The Hunter, B. mss., circa 1962-1979, consists of correspondence, notes, clippings, et cetera of Jim Jones, 1931-1978, and of Barton Hunter, 1908-1988, relating to Peoples Temple Christian Church of Indianapolis, Indiana and to Jones's Christian missions in South America.
The letters from Jones to Hunter are all from the period of time when he was on mission in Brazil. Other letters present are from other church members either to Jones or to Hunter, while the clippings relate to Jones's various "ministries," to the deaths in Guyana, and to the appeal of cults.
Collection size: 27 items
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence, arranged chronologically, and II. Clippings, etc.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1999/2000
Jonestown Mass Suicide, Jonestown, Guyana, 1978; Indiana University -- Alumni and alumnae; Religious leaders -- Indiana; Jones, Jim, 1931-1978; Hunter, Barton, 1908-1988
- Correspondence 1962. Letters from Jim Jones to Reverand Dr. Barton Hunter (File 1)
  - 1962, June 20. A.L.S. 18p. enclosing a 2 cruzeiros nore of Brazilian currency accompanied by envelope (File 1)
  - 1962, July 15. A.L.S. 6p. enclosing a 10 cruzeiros note of Brazilian currencty and eight (7 cent) United States airmal postage stamps accompanied by envelope (File 1)
  - 1962, [August]. A.L.S. 14p. enclosing a 5 cruzeiros note of Brazilian currency. First page stamped: received August 11, 1962 (File 1)
- Correspondence and notes 1971-1978 (File 2)
  - [1971, December 9]. Pastor Oscar Hill, St. Jude Missionary Baptist Church, Indianapolis, Indiana. To Pastor Jones, People's Temple, Indianapolis, Indiana. A.L.S. 4p. date from accompanying envelope (File 2)
  - 1971, December 12. Timothy O. Stoen, Ukiah, California. To Dr. Barton Hunter, Indianapolis, Indiana. A.L.S. 1p. (File 2)
  - 1971, December 12. The Indianapolis Star, p.14, sec.2. State Psychology Board to Eye 'Prophet' Jones (File 2)
  - 1972, February 8. Receipt of funds for use of People's Temple Building for January meeting (File 2)
  - 1972. Various notes re: telephone calls (File 2)
  - 1978, November 20. Pablo Stone, Managua, Nicaragua. To Dr. Robert A. Thomas, Indianapolis, Indiana T.L.S. 2p. (copy to Dorothy and Barton Hunter) (File 2)
  - 1978, December 12. Dorothy Hunter. To Pablo Stone, Mangua, Nicaragua. T(carbon)L. 2p. (File 2)
- Clippings, et cetera 1971-1979. Re: Jim Jones, the People's Temple of Guyana, the cult deaths, an interview with Barton Hunter about his relationship with Jones in the 1950s and 60s, et cetera (File 3)